<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en-US"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en-US" /><updated>2022-05-25T15:39:56+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Laura Logozzo</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>lauralogozzo</name></author><entry><title type="html">Contributions of Fe(III) to UV–Vis absorbance in river water: a case study on the Connecticut River and argument for the systematic tandem measurement of Fe(III) and CDOM</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/publications/2022/05/16/Logozzo/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Contributions of Fe(III) to UV–Vis absorbance in river water: a case study on the Connecticut River and argument for the systematic tandem measurement of Fe(III) and CDOM" /><published>2022-05-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-05-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/publications/2022/05/16/Logozzo</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/publications/2022/05/16/Logozzo/">&lt;h5 id=&quot;logozzo-l-martin-j-mcarthur-j-raymond-p-&quot;&gt;Logozzo, L., Martin, J., McArthur, J., Raymond, P. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;h6 id=&quot;may-2022--biogeochemistry&quot;&gt;May 2022 · &lt;em&gt;Biogeochemistry&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;figure  figure--center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/images/FARM-fall-cropped.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;&quot; height=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
Dissolved organic matter (DOM) impacts the structure and function of aquatic ecosystems. 
DOM absorbs light in the UV and visible (UV–Vis) wavelengths, thus impacting light 
attenuation. Because absorption by DOM depends on its composition, UV–Vis absorbance is 
used to constrain DOM composition, source, and amount. Ferric iron, Fe(III), also absorbs 
in the UV–Vis; when Fe(III) is present, DOM-attributed absorbance is overestimated. Here, 
we explore how differing behavior of DOM and Fe(III) at the catchment scale impacts UV–Vis 
absorbance and evaluate how system-specific variability impacts the effectiveness of 
existing Fe(III) correction factors in a temperate watershed. We sampled five sites 
in the Connecticut River mainstem bi-weekly for ~ 1.5 years, and seven sites in the 
Connecticut River watershed once during the summer 2019. We utilized size fractionation 
to isolate the impact of DOM and Fe(III) on absorbance and show that variable contributions 
of Fe(III) to absorbance at 254 nm (a&lt;font size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;sub&gt;254&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/font&gt;) and 412 nm 
(a&lt;font size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;sub&gt;412&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/font&gt;) by size fraction complicates 
correction for Fe(III). We demonstrate that the overestimation of DOM-attributed absorbance
by Fe(III) is correlated to the Fe(III):dissolved organic carbon concentration ratio; 
thus, overestimation can be high even when Fe(III) is low. a&lt;font size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;sub&gt;254&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/font&gt; overestimation is highly
variable even within a single system, but can be as high as 53%. Finally, we illustrate 
that UV-Vis overestimation might impart bias to seasonal, discharge, and land-use trends
in DOM quality. Together, these findings argue that Fe(III) should be measured in tandem
with UV–Vis absorbance for estimates of CDOM composition or amount.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1007/s10533-022-00937-5&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Read more&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>lauralogozzo</name></author><category term="Publications" /><category term="sticky" /><summary type="html">Logozzo, L., Martin, J., McArthur, J., Raymond, P. May 2022 · Biogeochemistry Dissolved organic matter (DOM) impacts the structure and function of aquatic ecosystems. DOM absorbs light in the UV and visible (UV–Vis) wavelengths, thus impacting light attenuation. Because absorption by DOM depends on its composition, UV–Vis absorbance is used to constrain DOM composition, source, and amount. Ferric iron, Fe(III), also absorbs in the UV–Vis; when Fe(III) is present, DOM-attributed absorbance is overestimated. Here, we explore how differing behavior of DOM and Fe(III) at the catchment scale impacts UV–Vis absorbance and evaluate how system-specific variability impacts the effectiveness of existing Fe(III) correction factors in a temperate watershed. We sampled five sites in the Connecticut River mainstem bi-weekly for ~ 1.5 years, and seven sites in the Connecticut River watershed once during the summer 2019. We utilized size fractionation to isolate the impact of DOM and Fe(III) on absorbance and show that variable contributions of Fe(III) to absorbance at 254 nm (a254) and 412 nm (a412) by size fraction complicates correction for Fe(III). We demonstrate that the overestimation of DOM-attributed absorbance by Fe(III) is correlated to the Fe(III):dissolved organic carbon concentration ratio; thus, overestimation can be high even when Fe(III) is low. a254 overestimation is highly variable even within a single system, but can be as high as 53%. Finally, we illustrate that UV-Vis overestimation might impart bias to seasonal, discharge, and land-use trends in DOM quality. Together, these findings argue that Fe(III) should be measured in tandem with UV–Vis absorbance for estimates of CDOM composition or amount. Read more</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/FARM-fall-cropped.JPG" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/FARM-fall-cropped.JPG" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Does photomineralization of dissolved organics matter in temperate rivers?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/publications/2021/07/05/Maavara/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Does photomineralization of dissolved organics matter in temperate rivers?" /><published>2021-07-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-07-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/publications/2021/07/05/Maavara</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/publications/2021/07/05/Maavara/">&lt;h5 id=&quot;maavara-t-logozzo-l-stubbins-a-aho-k-brinkerhoff-c-hosen-j-raymond-p-&quot;&gt;Maavara, T., Logozzo, L., Stubbins, A., Aho, K., Brinkerhoff, C., Hosen, J., Raymond, P. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;h6 id=&quot;july-2021--journal-of-geophysical-research-biogeosciences&quot;&gt;July 2021 · &lt;em&gt;Journal of Geophysical Research: Biogeosciences&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;figure  figure--center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/images/THOM-thumbnail.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;&quot; height=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
Sunlight can oxidize dissolved organic carbon (DOC) to dissolved inorganic carbon (DIC) 
in freshwaters. The importance of complete photooxidation, or photomineralization, as a 
sink for DOC remains unclear in temperate rivers, as most estimates are restricted to 
lakes, high latitude rivers, and coastal river plumes. In this study, we construct a model 
representing over 75,000 river reaches in the Connecticut River Watershed (CRW), USA, to 
calculate spectrally resolved photomineralization. We test the hypothesis that 
photomineralization is a negligible DOC sink across all reaches and flow conditions 
relative to DOC fluxes. Our model quantifies reaction rates and transport drivers within 
the river reaches for the ranges of flow conditions, incoming solar irradiance, and canopy 
cover shading observed throughout the year. Our model predicts average daily areal 
photomineralization rates ranging from 1.16 mg-C m−2 day−1 in low flow river reaches in 
the winter, to 18.33 mg-C m−2 day−1 in high flow river reaches during the summer. Even for
 high photomineralization fluxes, corresponding photomineralization uptake velocities are 
 typically at least an order of magnitude smaller than those reported for other instream 
 processes. We calculate DOC elimination by photomineralization relative to DOC fluxes 
 through individual stream reaches as well as the entire riverine portion of the CRW. 
 We find that relative photomineralization fluxes are highest in summer drought conditions
  in low order streams. In median flows and mean light intensities, for an average 
  watershed travel distance, 3%–5% of the DOC fluxes are eliminated, indicating that 
  photomineralization is a minor DOC sink in temperate rivers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1029/2021JG006402&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Read more&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>lauralogozzo</name></author><category term="Publications" /><category term="sticky" /><summary type="html">Maavara, T., Logozzo, L., Stubbins, A., Aho, K., Brinkerhoff, C., Hosen, J., Raymond, P. July 2021 · Journal of Geophysical Research: Biogeosciences Sunlight can oxidize dissolved organic carbon (DOC) to dissolved inorganic carbon (DIC) in freshwaters. The importance of complete photooxidation, or photomineralization, as a sink for DOC remains unclear in temperate rivers, as most estimates are restricted to lakes, high latitude rivers, and coastal river plumes. In this study, we construct a model representing over 75,000 river reaches in the Connecticut River Watershed (CRW), USA, to calculate spectrally resolved photomineralization. We test the hypothesis that photomineralization is a negligible DOC sink across all reaches and flow conditions relative to DOC fluxes. Our model quantifies reaction rates and transport drivers within the river reaches for the ranges of flow conditions, incoming solar irradiance, and canopy cover shading observed throughout the year. Our model predicts average daily areal photomineralization rates ranging from 1.16 mg-C m−2 day−1 in low flow river reaches in the winter, to 18.33 mg-C m−2 day−1 in high flow river reaches during the summer. Even for high photomineralization fluxes, corresponding photomineralization uptake velocities are typically at least an order of magnitude smaller than those reported for other instream processes. We calculate DOC elimination by photomineralization relative to DOC fluxes through individual stream reaches as well as the entire riverine portion of the CRW. We find that relative photomineralization fluxes are highest in summer drought conditions in low order streams. In median flows and mean light intensities, for an average watershed travel distance, 3%–5% of the DOC fluxes are eliminated, indicating that photomineralization is a minor DOC sink in temperate rivers. Read more</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/THOM-thumbnail.PNG" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/THOM-thumbnail.PNG" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Highest rates of gross primary productivity maintained despite CO2 depletion in a temperate river network</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/publications/2021/05/05/Aho/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Highest rates of gross primary productivity maintained despite CO2 depletion in a temperate river network" /><published>2021-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/publications/2021/05/05/Aho</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/publications/2021/05/05/Aho/">&lt;h5 id=&quot;aho-k-hosen-j-logozzo-l-mcgillis-w-raymond-p-&quot;&gt;Aho, K., Hosen, J., &lt;strong&gt;Logozzo, L.&lt;/strong&gt;, McGillis, W., Raymond, P. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;h6 id=&quot;may-2021--limnology-and-oceanography-letters&quot;&gt;May 2021 · &lt;em&gt;Limnology and Oceanography Letters&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;figure  figure--center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/images/THOM-thumbnail.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;&quot; height=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
Aquatic primary productivity produces oxygen (O2) and consumes carbon dioxide (CO2) in a 
ratio of ~1.2. However, in aquatic ecosystems, dissolved CO2 concentrations can be low, 
potentially limiting primary productivity. Here, results show that a large drainage basin 
maintains its highest levels of gross primary productivity (GPP) when dissolved CO2 is 
diminished or undetectable due to photosynthetic uptake. Data show that, after CO2 is 
depleted, bicarbonate, an ionized form of inorganic carbon, supports these high levels of 
productivity. In fact, outputs from a process-based model suggest that bicarbonate can 
support up to ~58% of GPP under the most productive conditions. This is the first evidence
 that high levels of aquatic GPP are sustained in a riverine drainage network despite CO2 
 depletion, which has implications for freshwater ecology, biogeochemistry, and isotopic 
 analysis.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1002/lol2.10195&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Read more&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>lauralogozzo</name></author><category term="Publications" /><summary type="html">Aho, K., Hosen, J., Logozzo, L., McGillis, W., Raymond, P. May 2021 · Limnology and Oceanography Letters Aquatic primary productivity produces oxygen (O2) and consumes carbon dioxide (CO2) in a ratio of ~1.2. However, in aquatic ecosystems, dissolved CO2 concentrations can be low, potentially limiting primary productivity. Here, results show that a large drainage basin maintains its highest levels of gross primary productivity (GPP) when dissolved CO2 is diminished or undetectable due to photosynthetic uptake. Data show that, after CO2 is depleted, bicarbonate, an ionized form of inorganic carbon, supports these high levels of productivity. In fact, outputs from a process-based model suggest that bicarbonate can support up to ~58% of GPP under the most productive conditions. This is the first evidence that high levels of aquatic GPP are sustained in a riverine drainage network despite CO2 depletion, which has implications for freshwater ecology, biogeochemistry, and isotopic analysis. Read more</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Laura_Portrait2.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Laura_Portrait2.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Photochemical and Microbial Degradation of Chromophoric Dissolved Organic Matter Exported from Tidal Marshes</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/publications/2021/03/09/Logozzo/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Photochemical and Microbial Degradation of Chromophoric Dissolved Organic Matter Exported from Tidal Marshes" /><published>2021-03-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-03-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/publications/2021/03/09/Logozzo</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/publications/2021/03/09/Logozzo/">&lt;h5 id=&quot;logozzo-l-tzortziou-m-neale-p-clark-b-&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Logozzo, L.&lt;/strong&gt;, Tzortziou, M., Neale, P., Clark, B. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;h6 id=&quot;march-2021--journal-of-geophysical-research-biogeosciences&quot;&gt;March 2021 · &lt;em&gt;Journal of Geophysical Research: Biogeosciences&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;figure  figure--center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/images/GCReW.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;&quot; height=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
Wetlands export chromophoric dissolved organic matter (CDOM) to estuaries, 
where CDOM is removed and transformed through biotic and abiotic process, subsequently 
impacting nutrient cycling, light availability, ecosystem metabolism, and phytoplankton 
activity. We examined the bioavailability and photoreactivity of CDOM exported from four 
Chesapeake Bay tidal marshes across three seasons and along an estuarine salinity gradient 
using three incubation treatments: 14‐day microbial (MD), 7‐day combined 
photochemical/microbial (PB+MD), and 7‐day microbial incubation after photobleaching 
(MD after PB). CDOM absorption at 300 nm (aCDOM300) and dissolved organic carbon (DOC) 
concentrations showed strong seasonality, with minima in winter, but CDOM quality 
(absorption spectral slopes, fluorescence component ratios) was less variable seasonally. 
PB+MD over 7 days decreased aCDOM300 (–56.0%), humic‐like fluorescence (–67.6%), 
and DOC (–17.8%), but increased the spectral slope ratio SR (=S275‐295/S300‐350) (+94.8%), 
suggesting a decrease in CDOM molecular weight. Photochemistry dominated the PB+MD 
treatment. Photoreactivity was greater during the winter and in marsh/watershed versus 
down‐estuary sites, likely due to less previous light exposure. Prior photobleaching 
increased the bioavailability of marsh‐exported CDOM, resulting in a greater loss of 
aCDOM300 and DOC, and a greater increase in humic‐like fluorescence (–6.0%, –5.9%, and 
+18.4% change, respectively, over 7‐day MD after PB incubations, versus –2.8%, –5.5%, and 
+2.6% change, respectively, over 14‐day MD incubations). CDOM exported from a marsh 
downstream of a major wastewater treatment plant showed the greatest photoreactivity 
and bioavailability. This highlights the significance of human activity on estuarine 
CDOM quality and biogeochemical cycles.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1029/2020JG005744&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Read more&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>lauralogozzo</name></author><category term="Publications" /><summary type="html">Logozzo, L., Tzortziou, M., Neale, P., Clark, B. March 2021 · Journal of Geophysical Research: Biogeosciences Wetlands export chromophoric dissolved organic matter (CDOM) to estuaries, where CDOM is removed and transformed through biotic and abiotic process, subsequently impacting nutrient cycling, light availability, ecosystem metabolism, and phytoplankton activity. We examined the bioavailability and photoreactivity of CDOM exported from four Chesapeake Bay tidal marshes across three seasons and along an estuarine salinity gradient using three incubation treatments: 14‐day microbial (MD), 7‐day combined photochemical/microbial (PB+MD), and 7‐day microbial incubation after photobleaching (MD after PB). CDOM absorption at 300 nm (aCDOM300) and dissolved organic carbon (DOC) concentrations showed strong seasonality, with minima in winter, but CDOM quality (absorption spectral slopes, fluorescence component ratios) was less variable seasonally. PB+MD over 7 days decreased aCDOM300 (–56.0%), humic‐like fluorescence (–67.6%), and DOC (–17.8%), but increased the spectral slope ratio SR (=S275‐295/S300‐350) (+94.8%), suggesting a decrease in CDOM molecular weight. Photochemistry dominated the PB+MD treatment. Photoreactivity was greater during the winter and in marsh/watershed versus down‐estuary sites, likely due to less previous light exposure. Prior photobleaching increased the bioavailability of marsh‐exported CDOM, resulting in a greater loss of aCDOM300 and DOC, and a greater increase in humic‐like fluorescence (–6.0%, –5.9%, and +18.4% change, respectively, over 7‐day MD after PB incubations, versus –2.8%, –5.5%, and +2.6% change, respectively, over 14‐day MD incubations). CDOM exported from a marsh downstream of a major wastewater treatment plant showed the greatest photoreactivity and bioavailability. This highlights the significance of human activity on estuarine CDOM quality and biogeochemical cycles. Read more</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Laura_Portrait2.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Laura_Portrait2.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Effects of Trace Narasin on the Biogeochemical N-Cycle in a Cultivated Sandy Loam</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/publications/2020/05/10/DeVries/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Effects of Trace Narasin on the Biogeochemical N-Cycle in a Cultivated Sandy Loam" /><published>2020-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/publications/2020/05/10/DeVries</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/publications/2020/05/10/DeVries/">&lt;h5 id=&quot;devries-s-loving-m--logozzo-l-zhang-p-block-k-&quot;&gt;DeVries, S., Loving, M.,  &lt;strong&gt;Logozzo, L.&lt;/strong&gt;, Zhang, P., Block, K. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;h6 id=&quot;may-2020--science-of-the-total-environment&quot;&gt;May 2020 · &lt;em&gt;Science of the Total Environment&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;figure  figure--center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;https://ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0048969720305416-ga1_lrg.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;&quot; height=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
Narasin is an antibiotic administered to broiler chickens to prevent coccidiosis. 
After storage, excreta containing parent narasin compounds is commonly spread as nitrogen fertilizer, 
yielding initial soil concentrations in the low μg·kg−1 range. In soil, antibiotics have 
been found to modify one or more pathways in the biogeochemical nitrogen cycle. The concentrations 
tested are often too high to be considered environmentally relevant, despite evidence that 
sub-therapeutic doses may also be disruptive. We conducted soil mesocosm experiments to 
determine the overall impact of trace narasin on major nitrogen pools and fluxes in soils 
treated with 0, 1, 10, 100, or 1000 ng·kg−1 narasin. Water content in the mesocosms varied 
from 40% to 80% water-filled pore space (WFPS), simulating a range of different redox 
conditions. Under aerobic conditions (40% WFPS), exposure to narasin inhibited nitrification, 
yielding increases in soil ammonium by up to 76%, perhaps by targeting nitrifying fungi. 
Under the same conditions, narasin caused soil nitrate concentrations to decline 17–39%. 
When the soil was near saturation (80% WFPS), nitrate increased by an average of 30%. 
Mass balances and isotopic enrichment of N2O indicate that NAR may also affect anammox and 
the rate of nitrifier nitrification/denitrification. In aerobic soils, N2O flux increased 
with antibiotic dose and the rise in flux strongly correlates to the N2O:N2 product ratio 
from dentification. This relationship suggests that N2O flux may increase in soils exposed 
to narasin even when total denitrification is modestly inhibited. We conclude that trace 
concentrations of narasin can significantly modify biogeochemical activities in soil on 
short timescales. Our results indicate the potential for extremely low concentrations of 
antibiotics to impact agricultural productivity, terrestrial N2O flux, and non-point source 
nitrogen pollution.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0048969720305416?via%3Dihub&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Read more&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>lauralogozzo</name></author><category term="Publications" /><summary type="html">DeVries, S., Loving, M., Logozzo, L., Zhang, P., Block, K. May 2020 · Science of the Total Environment Narasin is an antibiotic administered to broiler chickens to prevent coccidiosis. After storage, excreta containing parent narasin compounds is commonly spread as nitrogen fertilizer, yielding initial soil concentrations in the low μg·kg−1 range. In soil, antibiotics have been found to modify one or more pathways in the biogeochemical nitrogen cycle. The concentrations tested are often too high to be considered environmentally relevant, despite evidence that sub-therapeutic doses may also be disruptive. We conducted soil mesocosm experiments to determine the overall impact of trace narasin on major nitrogen pools and fluxes in soils treated with 0, 1, 10, 100, or 1000 ng·kg−1 narasin. Water content in the mesocosms varied from 40% to 80% water-filled pore space (WFPS), simulating a range of different redox conditions. Under aerobic conditions (40% WFPS), exposure to narasin inhibited nitrification, yielding increases in soil ammonium by up to 76%, perhaps by targeting nitrifying fungi. Under the same conditions, narasin caused soil nitrate concentrations to decline 17–39%. When the soil was near saturation (80% WFPS), nitrate increased by an average of 30%. Mass balances and isotopic enrichment of N2O indicate that NAR may also affect anammox and the rate of nitrifier nitrification/denitrification. In aerobic soils, N2O flux increased with antibiotic dose and the rise in flux strongly correlates to the N2O:N2 product ratio from dentification. This relationship suggests that N2O flux may increase in soils exposed to narasin even when total denitrification is modestly inhibited. We conclude that trace concentrations of narasin can significantly modify biogeochemical activities in soil on short timescales. Our results indicate the potential for extremely low concentrations of antibiotics to impact agricultural productivity, terrestrial N2O flux, and non-point source nitrogen pollution. Read more</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Laura_Portrait2.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/Laura_Portrait2.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>